<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Monad-transformers | Dmitry Antonyuk's blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://lomeo.github.io//blog/categories/monad-transformers/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://lomeo.github.io//"/>
  <updated>2016-11-27T01:50:58+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://lomeo.github.io//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Dmitry Antonyuk]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Back to the Future. Part I]]></title>
    <link href="http://lomeo.github.io//blog/2016/11/26/back-to-the-future-part-i/"/>
    <updated>2016-11-26T10:43:10+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://lomeo.github.io//blog/2016/11/26/back-to-the-future-part-i</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m going to write a series of posts on asynchronous computation that can
return no-result and how we deal with it in Scala. Don’t worry, it is just a
well-known Future over Option type.</p>

<h2>Intuition</h2>

<p>Recall what Future and Option are about.</p>

<p>The Future is just an asynchronous computation which will return the result…
eh… in future. But we already can use future combinators to work with this
result as it is already obtained.</p>

<p>The Option is much much simpler. It can be thought as a computation which can
return no result (frankly, not computation but value, but this difference does
not matter here). And yes, there are a lot of option combinators helping us to
work with wrapped value.</p>

<p>Future and Option can be combined in two different ways. The first one is about
the situation we need some future, but don’t sure if we may get it. E.g. we
have or haven’t some settings in config file, and depending on the availability
of this file, we should return a future which reads these settings or return no
future ‘cause there is nothing to read. Ok, we can encode such a type as
<code>Option[Future[T]]</code> type and this is not the type I will discuss here. Another
situation we could have is a future which can return no value. E.g. retrieving
some record from a database by it’s id. This record can exists or not.
Regarding this we can obtain the record or not. And the type for such
computation is <code>Future[Option[T]]</code>. See the difference?</p>

<h2>The Problem</h2>

<p>Well, let’s assume we need to find a record by it’s id and return it or, in the
event of absence, create a new one. The database API is reactive, all functions
return results in Future. There is already defined function <code>getPerson</code> which
return a person wrapped with Some if it exists or None if it doesn&rsquo;t. Let&rsquo;s
implement it as a function to see what types are used here:</p>

<pre><code class="scala">def getPerson(id: Int): Future[Option[Person]]

def getOrCreate(id: Int, person: =&gt; Person): Future[Person] =
  getPerson(id).map(_.getOrElse(person))
</code></pre>

<p>Sometimes there are different strategies to create a record, so we are
rewriting this to something like</p>

<pre><code class="scala">def getOr(id: Int, builder: =&gt; Future[Person]): Future[Person] = {
  getPerson(id).flatMap {
    case None =&gt; builder
    case Some(person) =&gt; Future(person)
  }
}
</code></pre>

<p>The code is pretty easy and neat, but later we need to do same things with
other tables/types and we write the boilerplate code over and over again. What
could we do with this?</p>

<h2>Implicits</h2>

<p>The first solution coming in mind is to use implicits parameterized by record
type. As a result we get additional methods for all Future[Option[T]]
instances. Let’s give it a try:</p>

<pre><code class="scala">implicit class FutureOption[T](future: Future[Option[T]]) {

  def getOrElse(default: =&gt; T): Future[T] =
    future.map(_.getOrElse(default))

  def orElse(default: =&gt; Future[T]): Future[T] =
    future flatMap {
      case Some(x) =&gt; Future.successful(x)
      case None =&gt; default
    }
  }

  // or, if you prefer combinator style
  // def orElse(default: =&gt; Future[T]): Future[T] =
  //   future.flatMap(_.fold(default)(Future.successful))
</code></pre>

<p>And it actually works. We don’t need <code>getOrCreate</code> or <code>getOr</code> functions
anymore.</p>

<pre><code class="scala">getPerson(id).getOrElse(newPerson)
getPerson(id).orElse(buildPerson)
</code></pre>

<h2>Monad Transformers</h2>

<p>Ok, no problems here. But could we go a little deeper?</p>

<p>First of all, let&rsquo;s stop and look what we have here. <code>Future[Option[T]]</code> type
combines two types together. Types like <code>Future</code> or <code>Option</code> are monadic types.
I don&rsquo;t want to discuss what monad is and what it isn&rsquo;t. Consider it like a
regular type having methods <code>flatMap</code> and <code>pure</code>. The first method is
well-known among scala programmers, so I skip the details. The second method is
just a constructor with one argument. For example, it is <code>Some</code> for <code>Option</code>
and <code>Future.successful</code> for <code>Future</code>. Wrap the value, nothing more.</p>

<p>Ok, so far so good. When we need to work with Future, we use top level calls,
when we need to work with Option, we lift it using <code>map</code> or <code>flatMap</code>. See
example:</p>

<pre><code class="scala">// map Future value
future.map(f) // f has type Option[A] =&gt; B

// map Option value
future.map(_.map(f)) // f has type A =&gt; B
</code></pre>

<p>Exactly as we did before in <code>getOrElse</code> and <code>orElse</code> methods. And this is a
place for generalization. See, everything we need from <code>Future</code> is
<code>Future.successful</code> (or <code>pure</code>) and <code>flatMap</code>. We used <code>map</code> as well, but it is
quite easy to implement it in terms of <code>flatMap</code> and <code>pure</code>:</p>

<pre><code class="scala">def map[B](f: A =&gt; B): F[A] =
    this.flatMap(x =&gt; implicitly[Monad[F]].pure(f(x)))
</code></pre>

<p>We say: &ldquo;Monad is a Functor&rdquo;. But who cares? :)</p>

<p>In fact, we may implement functions <code>getOrElse</code> and <code>orElse</code> for any monadic
type. As generic programmers we have to generalize these functions to support
all possible types. To get this we need to replace <code>Future[Option[T]]</code> type
with more generic one:</p>

<pre><code class="scala">class OptionT[F[_], A](val value: F[Option[A]]) {

  def map[B](f: A =&gt; B): OptionT[F, B] =
    new OptionT(value.map(_.map(f)))

  def flatMap[B](f: A =&gt; OptionT[F, B]): OptionT[F, B] =
    new OptionT(value.flatMap(_.fold(F.pure(Option.empty[B]))(x =&gt; f(x).value)))
}
</code></pre>

<p>This is a monad transformer. We can use Option inside any other monad. But
unfortunately this code fails for sure at least &lsquo;cause the compiler does not
aware of <code>value's</code> methods <code>map</code> or <code>flatMap</code>.</p>

<p>Here type classes come for the rescue. A little explanation how they work. We
define a special trait with methods <code>map</code> or <code>flatMap</code>, these methods accept
some value with generic type as argument, so concrete implementations of the
trait will aware of how to handle concrete type. See example:</p>

<pre><code class="scala">trait Monad[F[_]] {
  def pure[A](x: A): F[A]
  def map[A, B](m: F[A])(f: A =&gt; B): F[B]
  def flatMap[A, B](m: F[A])(f: A =&gt; F[B]): F[B]
}

implicit val futureMonad = new Monad[Future] {
  def pure[A](x: A): Future[A] = Future.successful(x)
  def map[A, B](m: Future[A])(f: A =&gt; B): Future[B] = m.map(f)
  def flatMap[A, B](m: Future[A])(f: A =&gt; Future[B]): Future[B] = m.flatMap(f)
}
</code></pre>

<p>Now we can use this monad implicitly to create generic OptionT</p>

<pre><code class="scala">case class OptionT[F[_], A](value: F[Option[A]]) {

  def map[B](f: A =&gt; B)(implicit m: Monad[F]): OptionT[F, B] =
    OptionT(m.map(value)(_.map(f)))

  def flatMap[B](f: A =&gt; OptionT[F, B])(implicit m: Monad[F]): OptionT[F, B] =
    OptionT(m.flatMap(value)(_.fold(m.pure(Option.empty[B]))(x =&gt; f(x).value)))
}
</code></pre>

<p>What about our functions <code>getOrElse</code> and <code>orElse</code>? Quite simple:</p>

<pre><code class="scala">class OptionT[F[_], A](val value: F[Option[A]]) {
  ...

  def getOrElse(default: =&gt; A)(implicit m: Monad[F]): F[A] =
    m.map(value)(_.getOrElse(default))

  def orElse(default: =&gt; F[A])(implicit m: Monad[F]): F[A] =
    m.flatMap(value)(_.fold(default)(m.pure))
}
</code></pre>

<p>Client code looks like:</p>

<pre><code class="scala">OptionT(getPerson(id)).getOrElse(newPerson)
OptionT(getPerson(id)).orElse(buildPerson)
</code></pre>

<p>We might use implicits here to convert <code>Future[Option[T]]</code> to
<code>OptionT[Future, T]</code> implicitly, but we won&rsquo;t.</p>

<h2>Meet Cats</h2>

<p>This section is the shortest one. <a href="http://typelevel.org/cats/">The cats library</a>
already provides <a href="http://typelevel.org/cats/datatypes/optiont.html">OptionT</a>.
So it is suffice to import <code>cats.data</code> to use <code>OptionT</code>.</p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/lomeo/futures-examples/">code examples</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
